The structure of a RewriteRule:

RewriteRule Pattern Substitution [OptionalFlags]

 The general structure of a RewriteRule is fairly simple if you already understand regular expressions. This article isn’t intended to be a tutorial about regular expressions though - there are already plenty of those available. RewriteRules are broken up as follows:

RewriteRule
-------------------------

This is just the name of the command. 


Pattern
------------------------

 A regular expression which will be applied to the “current” URL. If any RewriteRules have already been performed on the requested URL, then that changed URL will be the current URL. 


Substitution
------------------------

 Substitution occurs in the same way as it does in Perl, PHP, etc. 

You can include backreferences and server variable names (%{VARNAME}) in the substitution. Backreferences to this RewriteRule should be written as $N, whereas backreferences to the previous RewriteCond should be written as %N. 

A special substitution is -. This substitution tells Apache to not perform any substitution. I personally find that this is useful when using the F or G flags (see below), but there are other uses as well. 

VARIABLES:
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~

%{HTTP_HOST} = the basic url - e.g mysite.gov.il
%{REQUEST_URI} = the part that comes after the basic url. e.g. if the request is: mysite.gov.il/myWord then the variable will have the value "myWord"


OptionalFlags
-------------------------

 This is the only part of the RewriteRule which isn’t mandatory. Any flags which you use should be surrounded in square brackets, and comma separated. The flags which I find to be most useful are: 


C (chained with next rule)
CO=cookie (set specified cookie)
E=var:value (set environment variable var to value)
F (forbidden - sends a 403 header to the user)
G (gone - no longer exists)
H=handler (set handler)
L (last - stop processing rules)
N (next - continue processing rules)
NC (case insensitive)
NE (do not escape special URL characters in output)
NS (ignore this rule if the request is a subrequest)
P (proxy - i.e., apache should grab the remote content specified in the substitution section and return it)
PT (pass through - use when processing URLs with additional handlers, e.g., mod_alias)
R (temporary redirect to new URL)
R=301 (permanent redirect to new URL)
R=404 (return error code 404)
R=[code] - return another html error code
QSA (append query string from request to substituted URL)
S=x (skip next x rules)
T=mime-type (force specified mime type)


Redirect example 1:
==============================

block access to a url that ends with the word "user":

RewriteRule user($|/$) - [R=404]


Redirect example 2:
==============================

redirect a url that ends with the word "myWord" to a new url:

RewriteRule myWord https://a_new_url [NC,R=301,L]


Redirect example 3:
==================================

if you want to use a part of a url, you need to add a "RewriteCond" line before the rewrite line.

RewriteCond {%HTTP_HOST} (.+)$ [NC]
RewriteRule myWord https://%1/newWord [NC,R=301,L]

Notes:

RewriteCond: The pattern "(.+)" means ANYTHING and wrapping it in brackets - "()" allows using the value that the pattern captured for later use.

RewriteRule: The token "%1" is used to refer to the value that was captured in the RewriteCond between the brackets - "()".


Redirect example 4:
==================================



Redirect example 5:
==============================

RewriteEngine On    # Turn on the rewriting engine
RewriteRule    ^pet-care/?$    pet_care_info_01_02_2008.php    [NC,L]    # Handle requests for "pet-care"


RewriteRule - Tells Apache that this like refers to a single RewriteRule.

^/pet-care/?$ - The "pattern". The server will check the URL of every request to the site to see if this pattern matches. If it does, then Apache will swap the URL of the request for the "substitution" section that follows.

pet_care_info_01_02_2003.php - The "substitution". If the pattern above matches the request, Apache uses this URL instead of the requested URL.

[NC,L] - "Flags", that tell Apache how to apply the rule. In this case, we're using two flags. "NC", tells Apache that this rule should be case-insensitive, and "L" tells Apache not to process any more rules if this one is used.

!!!NOTE!!! - the L may cause 500 errors if it is mis-used!!!!

# Handle requests for "pet-care" - Comment explaining what the rule does (optional but recommended)


Redirect example 6:
==============================

RewriteEngine on
RewriteRule ^page/([^/\.]+)/?$ index.php?page=$1 [L]


 Let’s walk through that RewriteRule, and work out exactly what’s going on: 
^page/
 Sees whether the requested page starts with page/. If it doesn’t, this rule will be ignored. 
([^/.]+)
 Here, the enclosing brackets signify that anything that is matched will be remembered by the RewriteRule. Inside the brackets, it says “I’d like one or more characters that aren’t a forward slash or a period, please”. Whatever is found here will be captured and remembered. 
/?$
 Makes sure that the only thing that is found after what was just matched is a possible forward slash, and nothing else. If anything else is found, then this RewriteRule will be ignored. 
index.php?page=$1
 The actual page which will be loaded by Apache. $1 is magically replaced with the text which was captured previously. 
[L]
 Tells Apache to not process any more RewriteRules if this one was successful.



הקשחות
========================

* DENY XFRAME:

<module headers.c>
Header always append X-Frame-Options SAMEORIGIN
</module>

* Disable not needed modules:

remove the LoadModule directive for mod_dav, and mod_dav_fs modules the from the httpd.conf file
remove the LoadModule directive for mod_status


* להוסיף את השורה הבאה לקובץ .htaccess בתיקיית השורש של האתר כדי לבצע REDIRECT משגיאה "חסום (403) לשגיאת "לא קיים (404) על מנת להטעות האקרים:
ErrorDocument 403 /index.php



General Commands:
=====================================

apachectl -S - detailed output of settings checker results
apachectl -v - basic version info
apachectl -V - version info in details
apachectl -M - list loaded modules



LIST OF APACHE MODULES:
===========================================


Module 		Description

userdir 	Mapping of requests to user-specific directories. i.e ~username in URL will get translated to a directory in the server.
include 	Server Side Includes
autoindex 	Displays directory listing when no index.html file is present
alias 	Mapping of requests to different filesystem parts
status 	Displays server stats
negotiation 	Content negotiation
filter 	Smart filtering of request
version 	Handling version information in config files using IfVersion
as-is 	as-is filetypes
auth_digest	This module provides encrypted authentication sessions. However, this module is rarely used and considered experimental. Alternate methods of encrypted authentication are recommended, such as SSL. If the above functionality is unnecessary, comment out the related module.
setenvif 	Placing ENV vars on headers
authnz_ldap & ldap 	This module provides HTTP authentication via an LDAP directory
mime_magic 	This module provides a second layer of MIME support that in most configurations is likely extraneous
dav_module & dav_fs_module 	WebDAV is an extension of the HTTP protocol that provides distributed and collaborative access to web content. Due to a number of security concerns with WebDAV, its use is not recommended
info 	This module creates a web page illustrating the configuration of the web server. This is an unnecessary security leak and should be disabled
speling 	This module attempts to find a document match by allowing one misspelling in an otherwise failed request. If the above functionality is unnecessary, comment out the related module
proxy, proxy_balancer, proxy_ftp, proxy_http & proxy_connect 	This module provides proxying support, allowing Apache to forward requests and serve as a gateway for other servers
cache, disk_cache, file_cache and mem_cache 	This module allows Apache to cache data, optimizing access to frequently accessed content. However, not only is it an experimental module, but it also introduces potential security ﬂaws into the web server such as the possibility of circumventing Allow and Deny directives
ext_filter 	Response passed through external program prior to client delivery
headers 	HTTP Response/Request Header Customization
usertrack 	User activity monitoring via cookies
vhost_alias 	Dynamically configured mass virtual hosting
env 	Clearing/setting of ENV vars
cgi 	This module allows HTML to interact with the CGI web programming language
actions 	Action triggering on requests
suexec 	The suEXEC feature provides Apache users the ability to run CGI and SSI programs under user IDs different from the user ID of the calling web server




The following modules are loaded by a default source build:

authn_file_module (shared)
authn_core_module (shared)
authz_host_module (shared)
authz_groupfile_module (shared)
authz_user_module (shared)
authz_core_module (shared)
log_config
 

Configure an Apache web server for core dump on segmentation faults
===================================================================

1.Add line to /etc/httpd/conf/httpd.conf 

CoreDumpDirectory /tmp

2. Create script coredump.sh and put in /etc/profile.d 

	#!/bin/sh
	ulimit -c unlimited

3.service httpd configtest
4.service httpd graceful



Apache Module mod_include
===================================================================

If documents contain server-side include directives (SSI: The Include Command) of languages
other than the default extension (which is shtml) such as .js (javascript),

for example "<!--#include virtual="path/name_of_script.js" -->",

update module include (mod_include) settings to support .js as well:

By default in file configuration /etc/http/conf/httpd.conf you'll see this:

#######################################
AddType text/html .shtml
AddOutputFilter INCLUDES .shtml
##########################################

For javascript support add another extension - .js - like so:

######################################
AddType text/html .shtml .js
AddOutputFilter INCLUDES .shtml .js
##########################################


Don't forget to gracefully restart the Apache service after making this change.



Apache Module mod_deflate
===================================================================
The mod_deflate module provides the DEFLATE output filter that allows output from your server to be compressed before being sent to the client over the network.
 
Can be configured in a file http.conf or .htaccess or vhost.
Here is an example of enabling compression only for the html and xml  files,but can add any type of file 

###########################################
<Directory "/your-server-root/manual">
    AddOutputFilterByType DEFLATE text/html
    AddOutputFilterByType DEFLATE text/xml	
</Directory>
###########################################


# remove browser bugs
BrowserMatch ^Mozilla/4 gzip-only-text/html
BrowserMatch ^Mozilla/4\.0[678] no-gzip
BrowserMatch \bMSIE !no-gzip !gzip-only-text/html
Header append Vary User-Agent




Block access to httpd from  specific ip via Directive <Limit> 
===========================================================================
For block access from specific ip can be used directive  <Limit> in file conf of vhost or .htaccess or httpd.conf.

<Limit GET POST>
     Order allow,deny
     Allow from all
     Deny from 1.1.1.1	
</Limit>


Remove from header name apache (Server:apache)
=================================================================
For remove from header type(apache) of server need use module security (mod_security)
1.need install module
	rpm -ivh mod_security-2.7.3-5.el6.x86_64.rpm
2.In file conf /etc/httpd/conf.d/mod_security.conf

Need add line 
SecServerSignature " "




for check compression of site 

https://varvy.com/tools/gzip/



